JOSE J VALOORAN

Address: Dubai, UAE

Contact: +971 52 9199092 | Email: jose valooran@rediffmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/josejvalooran/

Skype ID: josejvalooran

SUPPLY CHAIN MANAGEMENT PROFESSIONAL

(Purchase & Supply Operations | Logistics | Procurement | Project Costing & Analysis | Production & Demand Planning)

PROFESSIONAL SNAPSHOT

CIPS & PMP Certified Supply Chain Management professional with over 10 years of progressive experience in a cross-cultural environment across driving customer & business process improvements and implementing cost rationalization measures to enhance operational efficiency as well as achieve optimal value for money in the field of Supply Chain, Procurement, Logistics, Delivery, and Service. Proven strengths across establishing systems & procedures for effective management of distribution operations with outstanding ability to provide total supply chain solutions to ensure cost-effective and smooth flow of materials & services. Ability to evaluate key performance indicators (KPIs), develop SOP's and profitability reporting while conducting ISO-based process audits, and creation of documents required for ISO. Extensive experience in managing shipments to airline customers across Europe, America, Africa, Asia, from different locations.

Added Expertise:

Supply Chain Management Sourcing

Techno-Commercial Operations **Project Control**

Operations Management Logistics

Vendor Development Outsourced Production

Customer Relationship Management

Strategic Alliances Negotiations

being the part of the Implementation team

Supplier Evaluation Material Management

Procurement Management Quality Assurance

Scheduling & **Planning Business Analysis**

Inventory Management Contract Management

Key Recent Career Accomplishments:

- Achieved profit margins equivalent to over 10% of total Net Profit from a single project by negotiating on both sides, driving distribution, and conducting Total Cost Analysis
- Delivered a gross profit figure equivalent to 7% of half-yearly sales by concluding a single project through conducting extensive negotiations, and total cost analysis as well as strategizing and executing distribution management plans
- Achieved a cost-saving of 10% year-on-year and a drastic drop in customer grievances by 60% (being part of ISO 10002 implementation/evaluation team) through collating and studying customer feedback, driving reengineering on existing analysis, scheduling, communication as well as distribution processes
- Delivered over 10% of total net profit and a gross profit figure equivalent to 7%
- Worked as the Management Representative/Internal Auditor to contribute to developing the entire ISO 9001 & 10002 process for the organization
- Efficaciously scheduled/planned/communicated with factories/suppliers/customers on production and distribution activities as a Supply Chain Manager
- Successfully handled extremely urgent/critical projects within the lead time and cost for the customers, ensuring to realize the best possible results and higher customer satisfaction
- Implemented CRM centered reorder analysis and conducted budget v/s actual analysis as part of processes and systems established in the firm
- Accomplished a project within 24 hours of span right from conceptualization to execution and implementation
- Effectively helped customers in implementing 8 new items in a short span of less than 1 month
- Developed Defect Prevention Report for the organization, conducted/ Coordinated Quality System Review as part of ISO Surveillance audit, and created a Quality Management System which contains artifacts for IBS becoming an IAPSP
- Improved process efficiency by creating new templates for HR and Admin. Department and successfully created a Project Completion report & best practices report for IBS Projects
- Recognized as an excellent team builder/strong team player who excels in mediating among multiple divisions of organizations and maintains productive relationships with staff, peers, and management

Handled shipments to more than 50 different locations worldwide

Saved 10% year-onyear and dropped customer grievances by 60%

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

JAN 2019 – PRESENT: AVIVA, DUBAI **Growth Path**

As Supply Chain Manager, (Jan 2019 onwards)

Key Deliverables:

- Led the entire gamut of supply chain activities, including planning, sourcing, purchase/production, inventory, logistics, distribution, and attaining better-quality process stability & delivery compliance along with training of team
- Implemented CRM & budget process, cost-benefit analysis, and cost reduction, costing, and correct estimates, drove continuous improvement & profitability initiatives for procurement, Logistics, and material management functions to optimize total cost of ownership and overall operation efficiency along with risk evaluation.

- Planned, scheduled & controlled all phases of delivery & inventory management and reviewed the operational practices, identified the areas of quality failures, and processed changes for qualitative improvement
- Identified, Evaluated, and Negotiated with vendors for supplies and services aimed at improved customer satisfaction.
- Planned & operated the funds for logistics ensuring optimum utilization of resources while meeting anticipatory orders and maximizing opportunities to leverage spend, improve quality, optimize cost and reduce risk
- Managed Warehouse Operations and Ensured optimum inventory levels for achieving cost savings without hampering the operational process and managed day-to-day supplies performance of vendors to ensure achievement of service, cost, delivery, and quality norms

OCT 2010 - DEC 2018: NOWARA GROUP, DUBAI

Growth Path

As Supply Chain Manager, (Jul 2014 – Dec 2018) As Assistant Supply Chain /Sourcing/ Operations Manager, (Jan 2012 – Jun 2014) As Supply Chain Executive, (Oct 2010 – Dec 2011)

Kev Deliverables:

- Led the entire gamut of supply chain activities, including planning, sourcing, purchase/ production, logistics, inventory, and attaining better-quality process stability & delivery compliance
- Transformed the commercial forecast into the meaningful demand forecast, for use in capacity planning, procurement, and logistics planning and process optimization along with improved end-user satisfaction
- Successfully managed the shipment of a single item of one customer to more than 50 different locations spread across worldwide
- Achieved improved process stability (ISO 9001 & 10002 certified), delivery compliance & customer satisfaction and improved profitability of orders by conducting extensive negotiation with suppliers based on priorities
- Identified and implemented cost reduction, drove continuous improvement & profitability initiatives for production, procurement, logistics, and material management functions to optimize total cost of ownership and overall operation efficiency
- Organized and **developed RFP and RFQ documentation** in compliance with the established policies and procedure to ensure that the requirements are captured effectively
- Planned, scheduled & controlled all phases of inventory management, including cost-benefit analysis and reviewed the operational practices, identified the areas of quality failures, and processed changes for qualitative improvement
- Achieved optimal cost savings on procurement processes by executing sub-contracting & co-makers buying and contract finalization with cost breakups and price variation clause
- Planned & budgeted the funds for procurement and sourcing of materials ensuring optimum utilization of materials while meeting anticipatory orders and maximizing opportunities to leverage spend, improve quality, optimize cost and reduce risk
- Ensured optimum inventory levels for achieving cost savings without hampering the operational process and managed day-to-day supplies performance of vendors to ensure achievement of service, cost, delivery, and quality norms
- Established Inward Stock Acceptance Process and set up Outward Stock Release Process, ensured all the stock/cartons are packed, labeled well before dispatch

Jun 2007 – Dec 2008: IBS Software Ltd., Trivandrum as Process Analyst Key Deliverables:

- Administered numerous projects/departments associated in compliance with ISO/CMMI/Tick IT/PCMM certification requirements of the organization
- Worked as **Process consultant cum Quality Assurance Executive** on multiple projects to drive in operational excellence
- Made vital contribution in supporting with analysis to different departments, including HR and Administration departments
- Successfully developed various reports, including Defect Prevention Report, Quality Management System, and innovative templates for the HR & Admin department of the organization for improving process efficiency
- Drafted project accomplishment report & the **best practices report for IBS Projects** in coordination with all stakeholders and successfully conducted quality system review as part of an ISO surveillance audit
- Rationalized new WBS template for projects, presented effective measures as part of the estimation task force, and conducted FP based estimation training
- Managed OPD area of CMMI (for CMMI Level 5 recertification), and developed documents required for version 1.2 of CMMI

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

- **PMP/ PMI,** USA, 2016
- CIPS-Diploma, Zabeel Dubai/ Chartered Institute of Purchasing and Supply UK, 2014
- M.I.B. (Master of International Business) in Operations & Finance, School of Management Studies, Cochin University, 2007
- **B. Tech.** (Electrical & Electronics), Mar Athanasius College of Engineering, M.G, University, 2004

TRAININGS

- PMI-PMP
- QMS/ ISO 2015 Lead Auditor
- CMMI Level 5, Version 1.2

- FP and WBS Estimation Techniques
- Document/Software Configuration tools
- Investment Analysis & Portfolio Management

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Configuration Tools: Sub Version, VSS

● Software Packages: MS-Word, Excel and Power Point

● ERP Package: Microsoft Dynamics 365, Tally ERP, FOCUS & SAP ARIBA

PERSONAL DETAILS

Date of Birth: Apr 1982 | Nationality: Indian

Visa Status: Employment
Driving License: Valid UAE

Languages: English, Hindi and Malayalam



Please scan to capture contact details